Finding Aid for Donald S. Leonard Papers 1925-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald S. Leonard Papers 1925-1966
Leonard, Donald S. (Donald Sparling), 1903-1976.
85530; Aa/2; UAm
Michigan State Police officer, 1923-1941, Michigan Civil Defense Director during World War II, State Police Commissioner, 1947-1951, Republican candidate for governor, 1954, served on Michigan Liquor Commissioner and as Detroit Recorders Court judge. Papers include extensive documentation of his service as Director of Civil Defense and State Police Commissioner and his political activities.
33 linear feet
1 oversize folders
1.55 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the family of Donald S. Leonard in 1977. Donor no. 6100
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Microfilm: Portions of the Case Files subseries (Box 18), including the files on the shooting of Walter Reuther, are available on microfilm.
Donald S. Leonard was one of the nation's most respected law enforcement officers during the 1940s and 1950s. During a long and varied career which spanned fifty years of service, Leonard was party to the professionalization of the State Police and the development within the state of modern police methods. His particular interests in law enforcement included police communications, the legal aspect of police work, and civil defense procedures.
Leonard was both police officer and public servant. He worked as Michigan Civil Defense Director during World War II, was appointed State Police Commissioner in 1947, and Detroit Police Commissioner in 1952. During the 1950s, Leonard was active in Republican Party politics in Michigan, running unsuccessfully three times for governor: in 1952, 1954, and 1956. Retiring from police work and party politics, Leonard continued his public service into the 1960s and 1970s first as Liquor Control Commission chairman, later as Detroit Recorder's Court Judge.
Donald S. Leonard was born in Detroit, Michigan in 1903. Following graduation from Northern High School, he attended Wayne University where he received a bachelor of arts degree in 1925 and a bachelor of laws degree in 1931. It was while attending college in 1923 that Leonard first joined the Michigan State Police as a trooper, partially as a means of financing his way through school. At Wayne, Leonard was elected president of his class for four consecutive years and lobbied successfully to change the school from a two year to a four year college. In addition, Leonard did graduate work at the University of Michigan Law School during the period of 1933-1934.
After his graduation, Leonard remained with the state police. He rose to the rank of captain in 1930; and in 1934, he became district commander of the Second District, which had responsibility for the metropolitan Detroit area. In 1945, Leonard was promoted to superintendent of the Uniform Division; and in 1946, he was appointed acting commissioner. In 1947, Governor Kim Sigler, who had been elected on a platform of "Cleaning up" state government, turned to Leonard to improve the administration and efficiency of the state police. After nearly twenty-five years of service with the state police, Leonard was appointed state police commissioner, succeeding long-time incumbent, Oscar Olander.
During his career with the state police, Leonard was active in many police organization, including the Southeastern Michigan Association of Chiefs of Police, the Michigan Association of Chiefs of Police (MACP), and the International Association of Chiefs of Police (IACP), all of which he served as president at various times. Leonard also served as a member of the Permanent Legislative Committee, a lobbying organization for Michigan police chiefs, sheriffs, circuit judges, and prosecuting attorneys. As an early advocate of the use of radio in police work, Leonard was member of the Associated Police Communications Officers and the IACP's radio and communications committees.
During World War II, Leonard took on numerous positions in the field of civil defense. In the summer of 1941, when he was member of an American civil defense mission, he toured England observing the effects of German bombing and examining the organization of English civil defense. After his return to the United States, he became a special consultant to Fiorello LaGuardia, U.S. Director of Civil Defense. In 1942, Leonard was appointed director of the Civilian Protection Division, Michigan Council of Defense, and State Commander of U.S. Citizens' Defense Corps of Michigan. In 1943, he was promoted to administrator of the Michigan Council of Defense following the resignation of Harold A. Furlong. After a reorganization, Leonard became director of civil defense, a post he held until 1951, when he was succeeded by Lester J. Maitland. During the period of 1943-1948, Leonard also served as state fuel administrator and chairman of the Governor's Fuel Committee.
In 1952, Leonard retired from the Michigan State Police to run for governor. He was succeeded as State Police Commissioner by Joseph A. Childs. In the 1952 Republican primary, Leonard ran against Fred M. Alger and William C. Vandenberg, but was defeated by Alger.
After the election, Leonard was appointed Detroit Police Commissioner by Mayor Albert E. Cobo, a position he held until 1954 when he resigned to run for governor once again. In 1954, Leonard defeated three other candidates in the Republican primary, but was defeated by Governor G. Mennen Williams in the general election.
In 1956, Leonard again ran for governor. This time he was defeated in the republican primary by Albert E. Cobo. After his retirement from the Detroit Police Department, Leonard entered private legal practice and did consulting work for various police agencies. In 1959 he ran for Detroit Recorder's Court judge but was defeated. He was appointed to the Michigan Liquor Control Commission by Governor George Romney in 1963, and served as chairman until 1966, when he resigned and was elected to Detroit Recorder's Court.
In addition to his other activities, Leonard served on numerous committees, including the Michigan Bar Association's Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, the Detroit Bar Association's Committee on Civil Rights, and the Detroit Board of Education's Committee on Equal Educational Opportunities. Leonard also taught law course at the State Police Recruit School and Metropolitan Police Academy of Michigan.
Leonard died in 1976.
Summary Contents List
Personal and Correspondence, 1925-1966 -- Boxes 1-3
Civil Defense
World War II Era, 1941-1946 -- Boxes 4-7
Fuel Shortages and Rationing, 1943-1950 -- Boxes 7-8
Post-World War II, 1947-1952 -- Boxes 8-13
Michigan State Police, 1929-1952 -- Boxes 14-20
Detroit Police Department, 1952-1954 --Boxes 20-21
Political Files, 1950-1956 -- Boxes 22-27
Organization and Activities Files -- Boxes 28-32
Audio-Visual Materials (photographs and sound recording) -- Box 33
Box 18 is available on microfilm.
The Donald S. Leonard collection is a valuable resource to researchers studying topics of law enforcement and civil defense and Michigan state politics and government. The Donald S. Leonard collection has been arranged into seven series: Personal and Correspondence, 1925-1966; Civil Defense; World War II Era, 1941-1946; Michigan State Police, 1929-1952; Detroit Police Department, 1952-1954; Political Files, 1950-1956; Organization and Activities Files; Audio-Visual Materials; Committee on Equal Educational Opportunities. Leonard also taught law course at the State Police Recruit School and Metropolitan Police Academy of Michigan.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Associated Police Communications Officers.; Civil defense.; Civil defense--Great Britain.; Civil defense--Illinois--Chicago.; Communism.; Crime.; Detroit (Mich.). Citizens Advisory Committee on Equal Educational Opportunities.; Detroit (Mich.). Police Dept.; Detroit (Mich.). Recorder's Court.; Detroit (Mich.)--Riot, 1943.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Hooper, Warren G.--Assassination.; International Association of Chiefs of Police.; Japan.; Judges--Michigan--Detroit.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Law enforcement--Michigan.; Leonard, Donald S. (Donald Sparling), 1903-1976.; Michigan Association of Chiefs of Police.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Courts.; Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan. Office of Civil Defense.; Michigan. Office of Director of Civilian Defense.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan State Bar Association.; Michigan. State Crime Commission.; Michigan State Police.; Police--Michigan.; Radio broadcasting--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Reuther, Victor G. (Victor George), 1912-2004; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; State Prison of Southern Michigan.; Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.; Wiretapping.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Airplanes.; Automobiles.; Civil defense.; Detroit (Mich.). Police Dept.; Flint (Mich.); Ford Motor Company.; Great Britain.; Horses.; International Association of Chiefs of Police.; Juliana, Queen of the Netherlands, 1909-2004; Laboratories.; Michigan Association of Chiefs of Police.; Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan State Police.; Motorcycles.; Police--Michigan.; Political elections--1952.; Political elections--1954.; Politics and government--1946-1960.; Port Huron (Mich.); Radio broadcasting--Michigan.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Riots.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Shakespeare Company (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; State Prison of Southern Michigan.; Sojourner Truth Homes (Detroit, Mich.); Strikes.; Tornadoes.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; Vandercook, Roy C., 1873-; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Baird, Andrew C.; Black, Eugene F., 1903-1990; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Childs, Joseph A.; Chotiner, Murray M., 1909-1974.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Dillinger, John, 1903-1934.; Feikens, John, 1917-2011; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Ford, Gerald Rudolph, 1889-1962.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Furlong, Harold Arthur, 1895-; Gaines, Harry Robert, 1891-1974.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; Maitland, Lester J.; Marshall, S. L. A. (Samuel Lyman Atwood), 1900-1977.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Ness, Eliot, 1903-1957.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Olander, Oscar G. (Oscar Gustaf), 1899-1963.; Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Scholle, August, 1904-1972.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Waite, John Barker, 1882-1967; Walsh, Frank R.; Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal and Correspondence
  Personal and Correspondence consists of three subseries. One contains biographical information about Leonard including articles written about him and articles written by him. The second, and largest subseries, is made up of general correspondence that is not directly related to any of the other topical series. Since there is substantial overlap between these correspondence files and the subject files, the researcher is advised to consult both this subseries in addition to the subject files for all of Leonard's correspondence on a particular topic. The last subseries consists of speeches, drafts of speeches, and notes and background material. An index to the more important correspondents represented in this and the following series has been prepared and is available at the library.
  - Personal
    - Biographical materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Personal materials (Box 1)
    - Promotions, assignments, and salary miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Articles about Leonard (Box 1)
    - Articles by Leonard (Box 1)
    - Clippings-largely personal (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - 1925-April 1953, 35 folders (Box 1)
    - May 1953-1966, 41 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches and related
    - Speeches programs and publicity (Box 3)
    - Speech texts 1929-1964, 30 folders (Box 3)
      (some gaps in dating)
    - Speech fragments and notes, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Civil Defense
  The Civil Defense series contains three subseries: World War II Era (1941-1946), Fuel Shortages and Rationing (1943-1950), and Post-World War II (1947-1952). Each of these subseries is further divided by name of organization and major subject areas. These subseries are basically office files, and include many reports, memos, pamphlets, and orders not directly related to Leonard, along with his personal notes and correspondence. There is also a large selection of printed civil defense pamphlets and books. These subseries also include some of the office files of Leonard's predecessor and successor as Michigan Civil Defense Director, Harold A. Furlong and Lester J. Maitland respectively. Of interest in the first subseries are materials accumulated during a study trip taken by Leonard to examine civil defense procedures in England in 1941. This subseries also has information pertaining to the Detroit race riot of 1943. The files on post-war civil defense contain documentation of preparations for possible nuclear attacks.
  - World War II Era 1941-1946
    - National Civil Defense
      - U.S. Office of Civilian Defense 1941-1944
        - Organizational charts (Box 4)
        - Newspapers and bulletins
          - OCD newsletter, 1941 (Box 4)
          - Defense and Victory, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
          - Observation post, 1942 (Box 4)
          - Civilian front, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
        - Press releases, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Inter-office memos October 1941-January 1942, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - War Traffic Control
          - Correspondence and meeting reports (Box 4)
          - Final reports (Box 4)
        - Report-Duties of Police in Civilian Defense (Box 4)
        - Reports-Civil Defense Fire Protection (Box 4)
        - Reports-Defense Communications (Box 4)
        - List of State Defense Councils (Box 4)
      - Civil Defense Study Trip to England 1941
        - Daily programs and itineraries (Box 4)
        - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Notes, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Trip reports-Housing by Harry M. Prince (Box 4)
        - Trip reports-Medical Administration by Huntington Williams, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - British civil defense publications-Ministry of Home Security (Box 4)
        - British civil defense publications-Home Office, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Commercial civil defense pamphlets, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - London civil defense region circulars (Box 4)
        - Manchester civil defense papers (Box 4)
        - Bristol and Nottingham civil defense (Box 4)
        - Miscellanea (Box 4)
        - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
      - Regional Civil Defense Cooperation 1942-1945
        - East Coast Conference of State Defense Directors-correspondence (Box 5)
        - Various state civil defense bulletins and newsletters (Box 5)
        - Various state civil defense and disaster plans (Box 5)
        - U.S.O.C.D. Protection Services Division and Industrial Protection Division Report October 1944 (Box 5)
        - U.S.O.C.D. Civilian War Services report May 1944 (Box 5)
        - Notes and memos on Organizational Principles and Conduct of the War (Box 5)
    - Michigan Civil Defense
      - Michigan Council of Defense 1942-1943
        - Annual reports, chronologies, budgets, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Personnel lists (Box 5)
        - Correspondence 1942-1943, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Papers re legal liability for Civil Defense Activity (Box 5)
        - Papers re M.C.D. meetings (Box 5)
      - Office of Director of Civilian Defense 1943-1946
        - Papers re passage of Michigan Civilian Defense Act of 1943, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Year-end roundups and chronology (Box 5)
        - Personnel lists (Box 5)
        - Administrative procedures (Box 5)
        - Official bulletins, orders, memos, 3 folders (Box 5)
          (bulletins dealing with a specific activity will be found in the file for that activity
        - Report-Realignment of Civilian Defense Protective Services, 1944) (Box 5)
        - Appropriations and payroll, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Report to Governor Kelly 1944 (Box 5)
        - Press releases (Box 5)
        - MCD Bulletin and Michigan OCD Bulletin 1942-1944 (Box 5)
        - Inter-office memos (Box 5)
        - Correspondence 1943-1945, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Meetings with Governor-agendas and notes (Box 5)
        - State disaster plans (Box 5)
        - Lists of Michigan communities, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Michigan Airport directory (Box 5)
        - Termination of Michigan O.C.D.
          - Correspondence and notes 1945-1948, 2 folders (Box 5)
          - Property accounting (Box 5)
      - U.S. Citizens Defense Corps of Michigan 1941-1945
        - Organizational statements and reports (Box 5)
        - Organizational charts (Box 5)
        - Personnel lists-part of Upper Peninsula, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Personnel lists-local commanders (Box 6)
        - Correspondence and notes (Box 6)
        - Training manual (Box 6)
        - Operational Plan-State Control Center (Box 6)
        - Operational Plan-Local Control Center (Box 6)
        - Sample forms (Box 6)
      - County and Municipal Defense Councils 1941-1945
        - Correspondence (Box 6)
        - Report on Berrien County Defense Council (Box 6)
        - History of Pontiac Defense Council (Box 6)
        - Tabulation of county and municipal defense councils, and allocation of equipment (Box 6)
        - List of members (Box 6)
      - Detroit Metropolitan Civil Defense Area 1941-1945
        - Establishment and administration (Box 6)
        - Organization-Plans (Box 6)
        - Organization-Correspondence (Box 6)
        - Budget and personnel (Box 6)
        - General correspondence (Box 6)
        - Organizational charts (Box 6)
        - Inventory of goods and services shortages in metropolitan Detroit (Box 6)
        - Volunteer, Detroit civil defense newspaper, 1944 (Box 6)
      - Michigan State Troops Officers' School 1943
        - Transcript of lectures (Box 6)
      - Civil Protection Programs 1941-1945
        - Air Wardens
          - Aircraft Detection Corps-Aircraft Warning Service
            - Correspondence May 1942-1944, 3 folders (Box 6)
            - Notes and lists (Box 6)
            - Publicity (Box 6)
          - Air Raid Warning System
            - Correspondence (Box 6)
            - Instructions and orders (Box 6)
            - Civilian instructions (Box 6)
            - Miscellaneous publications (Box 6)
            - New air raid warning signals 1943 (Box 6)
            - Air Raid Warning Test reports March 8, 1944 (Box 6)
            - Air Raid Warning Test reports May 10, 1944 (Box 6)
          - Japanese balloon attacks, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Buzz bomb attacks (Box 6)
        - Police Protection
          - County warning plan (Box 6)
          - Radio silencing plan (Box 6)
          - Survey of Michigan police departments (Box 6)
          - Detroit Riot 1943 (Box 7)
            - Correspondence and memos (Box 7)
            - Report and recommendations by Leonard (Box 7)
            - Mobilization plan (Box 7)
          - Berrien County guerrilla unit
            - Correspondence (Box 7)
            - Clippings (Box 7)
        - Fire Protection, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Gas Defense organization (Box 7)
        - Protection of water supply and bridges (Box 7)
        - Disaster command post exercises (Box 7)
        - Industrial plant protection
          - Correspondence and memos (Box 7)
          - Transcript of Wisconsin Plant Protection conference 1942 (Box 7)
        - Blood plasma and resuscitator availability (Box 7)
        - Michigan Bell Telephone Company and civil defense
          - Correspondence (Box 7)
          - Presentation of National Security Award (Box 7)
          - Emergency routines (Box 7)
          - Wartime emergency procedures (Box 7)
        - Practice blackouts, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Civilian Welfare Programs 1941-1945
        - Milk shortage, 4 folders (Box 7)
        - Housing (Box 7)
        - Soldiers' ballots (Box 7)
        - D-Day observance (Box 7)
        - VE and VJ Day plans (Box 7)
        - Food and salvage (Box 7)
  - Fuel Shortages and Rationing 1943-1950
    - Gasoline Rationing-Relaxation of rationing for deer hunters 1943
      - Correspondence September 1943-December 1943, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Notes (Box 7)
      - Press releases and clippings, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Coal Shortages 1943-1946
      - State and federal orders and plans (Box 8)
      - Press releases
        - U.S. Solid Fuels Administration, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Michigan Office of Civilian Defense (Box 8)
      - Correspondence and notes (Box 8)
      - Coal dealer bulletins and memos (Box 8)
    - Coal Shortages 1948-1950
      - Papers (Box 8)
    - Oil Shortages 1947-1948
      - Governor's Fuel Committee
        - Plans and reports (Box 8)
        - Meetings, minutes and notes (Box 8)
        - Press releases and radio transcripts (Box 8)
        - General correspondence 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - State Industry Advisory Committee (Box 8)
      - Interviews with oil industry officials (Box 8)
      - Local fuel shortages, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Fuel conservation program (Box 8)
      - Emergency fuel certificates (Box 8)
      - Truck weight and length restrictions (Box 8)
      - Oil industry reports, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Petty's oil letter (Box 8)
      - National Petroleum Council, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Congressional hearings (Box 8)
      - Federal Power Commission and Michigan Public Service Commission hearings (Box 8)
    - Fuel Shortages 1943-1950
      - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Post-World War II 1947-1952
    - National Civil Defense 1947-1952
      - Legislation (Box 8)
      - Planning meetings 1947-1948 (Box 8)
      - Bulletins and memos (Box 8)
      - Speeches and press releases (Box 8)
      - Radio broadcast transcripts (Box 8)
      - Reports
        - Civil Defense Highway Traffic Program, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Coordination of Fire Service in Civil Defense Planning by Frank C. McAuliffe (Box 8)
        - Mutual Aid (Box 8)
        - Damage from Atomic Explosion and Design of Protective Structures (Box 8)
        - Public Health and Civil Defense (Box 8)
        - Flood Emergency Manual-Wisconsin (Box 8)
    - Regional Civil Defense Cooperation 1947-1952
      - Summary Reports of State Civil Defense Activity (Box 9)
      - Interstate Civil Defense and Disaster Compact (Box 9)
      - Eastern Conference of State Civil Defense Directors, 2 folders (Box 9)